Register of the Institute of Pacific Relations. San Francisco Bay Region Division Records, 1944-1947
Hoover Institution Archives
Institute of Pacific Relations. San Francisco Bay Region Division Records,
1944-1947
55003
Institute of Pacific Relations. San Francisco Bay Region Division
27 manuscript boxes, 1 card file box (11.6 linear feet)
Hoover Institution Archives Stanford, California 94305-6010
Correspondence, reports, memoranda, studies, and printed matter, relating to the study of political, social, and economic conditions in the Far East and of U.S. foreign policy in the Far East.
Administrative Information
Access
Collection open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Access Points
Pan-Pacific relations.; East Asia.; East Asia--Economic conditions.; East Asia--Foreign relations--United States.; East Asia--Politics and government.; East Asia--Social conditions.; United States--Foreign relations.; United States--Foreign relations--East Asia.
Historical Notes
The San Francisco Bay Region Division was one of seven semi-autonomous regional centers of the American Institute of Pacific Relations, a privately-financed organization founded in 1925 for the purpose of promoting investigation and discussion of the problems and mutual relations of the peoples of the Pacific area. The American Institute of Pacific Relations was itself a part of a larger, international Institute of Pacific Relations that between 1925 and 1961 included groups in Australia, Canada, France, Great Britain, Japan, Netherlands, New Zealand, the Philippines, and the U.S.S.R.
The San Francisco Bay Region IPR assisted the American IPR in local and national research, conducted a program of meetings and conferences, and promoted interest in and study of Pacific problems in its region. With a total of 400 members in 1946, it provided study groups, round tables, and teacher seminars. Its publications included a monthly periodical, Pacific News Letter, that reported IPR activities to members; a mimeographed bulletin, In Advance of the News, that contained information on Pacific war developments; and a third publication, New Library Materials, that listed new IPR library acquisitions.
Officers of the San Francisco Bay Region IPR during the 1944-1947 period were: Chairman, Ray Lyman Wilbur; Executive Vice Chairman, Lynn White, Jr.; Vice Chairman, Mrs. Alfred McLaughlin; Vice Chairman, Robert G. Sproul; Treasurer, Brayton Wilbur; Executive Director, Ernest B. Price (until January 1945) and Eugene Staley (after September 1945).
In June 1947, the San Francisco Bay Region IPR joined with other local organizations to form the World Affairs Council of Northern California, an independent civic enterprise for community education in world affairs. Although the San Francisco Bay Region IPR was formally dissolved at that time, many of its operations were continued by the Pacific Area Affairs Division of the World Affairs Council of Northern California.
In addition to the Records of the San Francisco Bay Region IPR, the Hoover Institution Archives maintains the Ray Lyman Wilbur Collection, which contains a large group of material relating to the IPR. Wilbur was Chairman of the American IPR during the periods 1925-1928, 1940-1941, and 1948-1949. The records of the American IPR central office and the records of the international IPR office were donated to the Columbia University Library in 1961 when the IPR disbanded.
(from Windows on the Pacific, Biennial Report, 1944 to 1946 of the Board of Trustees to the Membership of the American Council, Institute of Pacific Relations, Inc. and from the correspondence files of San Francisco Bay Region IPR Collection)
Series Description
- CORRESPONDENCE, 1944-1947 (Box 1-5)
  Correspondence of the Executive Director or his secretary, arranged alphabetically by name of correspondent.
- ADMINISTRATIVE RECORDS, 1944-1947 (Box 6-7)
  Reports, memoranda, lists, correspondence, press releases, and clippings, relating to administrative operations, arranged by subseries as listed.
- SUBJECT FILE, 1944-1947 (Box 7-13)
  Reports, studies, memoranda, correspondence, schedules, printed matter, and clippings, arranged alphabetically by subject.
- INCREMENT (Box 14-27)
Container List
- CORRESPONDENCE, 1944-1947
  - A--general (Box 1)
  - Adloff, Virginia T.
  - Aglion, Raoul (United Nations)
  - American Association for the United Nations
  - American-Russian Institute
  - Arnold, Julean
  - B--general
  - Belshaw, Horace
  - Borg, Dorothy
  - C--general
  - California Labor School
  - Carter, Edward C., Vice Chairman, American IPR
  - China-American Council of Commerce and Industry (Box 2)
  - China-American Council of the Institute of Social Research
  - Commission to Study the Organization of Peace
  - Committee on Foreign Relations, San Francisco
  - Conference for Democratic Community
  - Conference of Christians and Jews, San Francisco
  - Council for Civic Unity
  - Council of American-Soviet Friendship, San Francisco
  - Council on Foreign Relations, New York
  - Council on World Affairs, Cleveland
  - D--general
  - Dennett, Raymond
  - E--general
  - Eloesser, Herbert
  - English-Speaking Union
  - F--general
  - Far Eastern Democratic Society
  - Fisher, Galen M.
  - Foreign Information Groups (O.W.I.)
  - Freeman, Miller
  - G--general
  - Ganther, Mrs. John O., Jr.
  - Gerbode, Mrs. Frank
  - H--general (Box 3)
  - Heller, Mrs. E. S.
  - Holland, William L., Secretary General, International IPR, New York
  - Honolulu IPR
  - Hopkins, L. Arundel
  - Hunter, James J.
  - I--general
  - Institute of International Relations, Mills College
  - International Center
  - International Institute of San Francisco
  - J--general
  - Jacoby, E. H.
  - K--general
  - Keesing, Felix M.
  - L--general
  - League of Women Voters, San Francisco
  - Lilienthal, Philip
  - Los Angeles IPR (Box 4)
  - M--general
  - Mc--general
  - McLaughlin, Mrs. Alfred
  - N--general
  - Nelson, Donald
  - New York Office, American IPR, 1945-1947
  - Northwest IPR
  - O--general
  - P--general
  - Paige, Mrs. Harold L.
  - Price, Ernest B.
  - Q--general
  - R--general
  - Rogers, Mrs. W. Lister
  - S--general
  - San Francisco Bay Area Region Executive Committee (Box 5)
  - Sproul, Robert G., Vice Chairman, San Francisco Bay Area Region
  - Staley, Eugene
  - Stewart, Marguerite Ann, Secretary, American IPR, New York
  - T--general
  - U--general
  - United Service to China
  - V--general
  - Vezey, W. Curtis
  - W--general
  - Washington, D. C. IPR
  - White, Lynn, Jr., Executive Vice Chairman, San Francisco Bay Area Region
  - Wickett, F. A.
  - Wilbur, Brayton, Treasurer, San Francisco Bay Area Region
  - Wilbur, Ray Lyman, Chairman, San Francisco Bay Area Region
  - X,Y,Z--general
- ADMINISTRATIVE RECORDS, 1944-1947
  - General (Box 6)
  - Organization--Officers, Committees, Relations with Other Organizations
  - Relations with American IPR
  - Reorganization of Executive Committee and Board of Directors
  - Board of Directors
  - Executive Committee Minutes
  - Monthly Reports to New York Office
  - Annual Reports
  - Committees
    - IPR Conferences
    - Control of Disbursements
    - Education
    - Finance
    - Library
    - Membership
    - Policy and Organization Development
    - Program and Publications
  - Pacific News Letter
  - Releases and Press Clippings
  - Publicity Information
  - Financial Records
    - Responses to Admiral Greenslade's Letter, November 20, 1944
    - Returns from Follow-up Letters
    - Briggs Trust, 1945 (Box 7)
    - Columbia Foundation, 1945
    - People's Fund, 1945
    - Rosenberg Foundation, 1945
    - Letters Requesting Financial Support, 1945-1946
    - Finance Luncheon, 1946
    - Finance Luncheon, Hand-out Materials
    - Financial Campaign, 1947
- SUBJECT FILE, 1944-1947
  - American Council of the IPR, New York Office (Box 7)
    - By-Laws, Incorporation, 1944-1946
    - Board of Trustees
    - Executive Committee
    - 1945 Conference, Hot Springs, Virginia (Box 8)
    - 1947 Conference, Coronado, California
    - Research Advisory Committee (Box 9)
    - Promotion
    - International Research Committee
  - "American Interest in the Future of Dependent Territories in Asia and Pacific"
  - American-Russian Study Group, Discussion Outline No. 1
  - Far Eastern Survey
  - Indonesian Issues and American Policy
  - Junior Executives Seminar Papers, No. 15, Nos. 50-80 (No. 60 is missing)
  - Kohlberg, Alfred E. (Box 10)
  - Kohlberg, Alfred E.--"An Analysis of Mr. Alfred E. Kohlberg's Charges Against the Institute of Pacific Relations"
  - Los Angeles Region of IPR
  - Los Angeles Visit, November 1945
  - New Library Material (Box 11)
  - Organizations Similar to IPR
  - Pacific Center Project
  - Pacific House
  - Pacific News Letters, 1944-1945, Miscellaneous Numbers
  - Pacific News Letters, 1946-1947, Miscellaneous Numbers (Box 12)
  - Pamphlet Publications, Drafts
  - Roundtable Conference on Future of Foreign Trade, March 9, 1946
  - San Francisco World Trade Center
  - Teachers Seminars, 1945-1946
  - Travel Timetables (Box 13)
  - United Nations Conference for International Organizations, April 1945
    - Delegates, Press Representatives, Others
    - Correspondence About Special Services and and Activities
    - Entertainment, Invitations
    - Replies to Correspondence
- INCREMENT
  - Aims, activities, organization, etc., 1945-46 (Box 14)
  - American Association of University Women (Burlingame), roundtable conference on postwar treatment of Japan, January 8, 1945
  - American Council (of the I.P.R.) Conference, Princeton, May 1946
  - Analysis of income and expenditures, 1944-46
  - Atom, general information, 1945-46
  - Atomic Bomb Conference, December 29, 1945
  - Auditor's report, 1945
  - Bank deposit statements
    - 1940
    - 1942
    - 1941 (Box 15)
    - 1943-44
    - 1946
  - Bank statements and cancelled checks
    - 1941-43
    - 1944-47 (Box 16)
    - Cancelled checks, 1943-44 (Box 17)
    - Carson, Colonel, meeting, November 16, 1945
    - Cash receipts, 1943-45
    - Check book
    - Check register, 1941-47
    - Check requisitions (Box 18)
      - 1940-42
      - 1943-44 (Box 19)
      - 1944-45 (Box 20)
      - 1946 (Box 21)
    - Check stub book. 1944-47
    - Chen, Y. G., luncheon-lecture, January 23, 1945
    - Chiang Mon-Lin tea, April 19, 1945
    - Chronicle Forum, 1946-47 (Box 22)
    - Conferences and roundtables, 1945-46
    - Correspondence
      - League of Nations, 1945
      - Student I.P.R., 1946-47
      - Miscellaneous, 1937-38, 1946-47, 1957
    - Council on Foreign Relations, May 10-11, 1946
    - Dependencies Conference, February 9, 1946
    - Dunn tea, November 5, 1946
    - Education project, 1944-45
    - Eggleston, Sir Francis, tea, March 27, 1946
    - "Emerging Political and Economic Issues in the Far East", teacher's seminar, Autumn 1945
    - Evatt luncheon, December 6, 1945
    - Executive Committee (Box 23)
      - General, 1945
      - Minutes of meetings, 1945-47
    - Films and moving pictures
    - Financial estimate, 1945
    - Financial reports, 1945-47
    - Financial statements, 1944-45
    - Foster, Jane, tea, "Revolt in Indonesia," January 11, 1946
    - Freeman luncheon, May 10, 1946
    - "The Future of Foreign Trade and Investment Across the Pacific," roundtable conference, March 1946
    - Grant, John B., luncheon-lecture, January 29, 1946
    - Greenbie tea, September 13, 1945
    - Greenslade reception, May 13, 1946
    - Howe, C. H., cocktail party, February 23, 1945
    - Hutchinson, Dr. Paul, luncheon-lecture, March 7, 1946
    - Jacoby, Professor H., tea, July 6, 1945
    - Johnson, Eric, tea, April 12, 1946
    - Keesing, Professor, "I.P.R. Conference Report," luncheon-lecture, February 13, 1945
    - Kiskaddon tea, January 8, 1946
    - Kunzru, Dr. N. N., tea, March 19, 1945
    - Lectures, correspondence, etc.
    - Lectures requested, but not accepted, 1946-47
    - Leebrick tea, July 30, 1946
    - Liang, Hubert, tea, March 12, 1945
    - Lindsay, Michael, March 7, 1946
    - Marquette, Dr. Jacques, luncheon-lecture, March 15, 1945 (Box 24)
    - Membership receipt-stubs, 1947
    - Mikheev, Vladimir, tea, February 16, 1945
    - Pacific Council Atlantic City meeting, January 26 - February 1, 1946
    - Pacific News Letter (San Francisco), 1946
    - Petty cash disbursements, pledges, contributions, etc., 1938-1945
    - Petty cash slips
      - 1942-43
      - 1944-46 (Box 25)
    - Programs
      - Borton, Hugh, May 2, 1947
      - De Bivort, Hervey G., April 22, 1947
      - Dustmoor, P. E., luncheon, June 4, 1947
      - Eloesser, Dr. Leo, luncheon, March 4, 1947
      - Fairbank, Wilma, March 24, 1947
      - First National Conference, April 1947
      - Maddox, William P., May 1947
    - Programs and events, 1945
    - Qurban tea, July 16, 1946
    - Radio programs, August 1946
    - "Reconstruction in Asia," teacher's seminar, Spring 1945
    - Research Advisory Committee, 1937, 1939
    - Robinson tea, September 30, 1946
    - Siamese Engineers tea, May 28, 1947
    - Smyth, H. D., "A General Account of the Development of Methods of Using Atomic Energy for Military Purposes Under the Auspices of the U.S. Government, 1940-45," August 1945 (Box 26)
    - Speakers, 1946-47
    - Staley, Eugene, "Some Problems of Economic Development in the Orient," December 1946
    - Staley lecture-luncheon, September 26, 1945
    - Stein, Gunther, luncheon, October 15, 1946
    - Stevens tea, September 4, 1946
    - Student conference on the colonial issue, January 11, 1946
    - Teacher's course, 1946-47
    - Telesco tea, March 26, 1946
    - Tsiang, T. F., tea, April 17, 1946
    - United Nations, 1946-47
    - Witholding tax, 1945, 1947
    - Yen, James, luncheon-lecture
    - Membership index (Box 27)